<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Grand Seignior's speech to the Ottoman forces at Belgrade who are now at wars with the Christians, 1683</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 5KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B23658</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">9677913</idno>
  <idno type="VID">204459</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2264196401</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing G1512</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">09677913</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B23658)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 204459)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1332:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Grand Seignior's speech to the Ottoman forces at Belgrade who are now at wars with the Christians, 1683</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Smith,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Austro-Turkish War, 1683-1699 --  Poetry.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Simon Charles </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb facs="tcp:204459:1"/>
            <head>THE <hi>Grand Seigniors</hi> SPEECH TO THE <hi>Ottoman</hi> Forces at <hi>Belgrade,</hi> who are now at Wars with the <hi>CHRISTIANS,</hi> 1683.</head>
            <div type="speech">
               <lg>
                  <l>MY <hi>Janyzary</hi>-Slaves, your Pow'r alone</l>
                  <l>I need not question to secure my Throne.</l>
                  <l>Nor can I doubt a Force so often try'd,</l>
                  <l>Which <hi>Christian</hi> Fields, with <hi>Christian</hi> Blood has dy'd:</l>
                  <l>Go on then boldly to dispose the Fates,</l>
                  <l>Of crazy <hi>Europe</hi>'s ill supported States,</l>
                  <l>Untill the trembling <hi>Princes</hi> of the <hi>West</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Bow to that Hand, which has subdu'd the <hi>East:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Let the deluded World be taught by you,</l>
                  <l>What to our <hi>Prophet</hi> and our <hi>Arms</hi> is due.</l>
                  <l>So Fight, as may our Enemies perswade,</l>
                  <l>A Pow'r, not humane does their States Invade.</l>
                  <l>Instruct the <hi>Christians</hi> in each Loss to read</l>
                  <l>How we of old, against Them did succeed.</l>
                  <l>In ev'ry Breach and Batt'ry, still relate,</l>
                  <l>The Story of our Honour, and their Fate.</l>
                  <l>In springing Moynes, or taking Bastions, tell,</l>
                  <l>Thus <hi>Candy,</hi> thus defenceless <hi>Rhodes</hi> once fell.</l>
                  <l>Recounting these, the better to inflame</l>
                  <l>Your Courage, no less than provoke their shame.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>By our great <hi>Prophet,</hi> and his <hi>Law,</hi> I vow</l>
                  <l>(No stronger Ties our <hi>Turkish</hi> Faith does know)</l>
                  <l>That petty Trifle call'd the <hi>Caesar</hi> of the <hi>West,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Emp'rour in Name, in Truth, but Fortunes Jest.</l>
                  <l>Mock't with th' Imperial Scepter, and a Crown,</l>
                  <l>Hector'd by Laws, by ev'ry Prince run down:</l>
                  <l>No longer shall be miserably Great,</l>
                  <l>A Purple Captive, and a Slave of State.</l>
                  <l>Not to the <hi>Empires Younger Brothers</hi> sue,</l>
                  <l>While tedious <hi>Diets</hi> slow Debates pursue.</l>
                  <l>These Mischeifs now no longer shall depend,</l>
                  <l>His Vassalage in pitty ought to end.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:204459:2"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>His Empire</hi> henceforth shall become my Care,</l>
                  <l>Th' <hi>Electors Lots</hi> my <hi>Bassa</hi>'s, be your Share.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Already for our Conquests to make way,</l>
                  <l>Our Foes divided, on each other Prey;</l>
                  <l>Revolted <hi>Teckley</hi> with his Friends does work,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Christians</hi> joyn gainst <hi>Christians</hi> for the <hi>Turk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Their <hi>Diets Factions</hi> promise fair, that we</l>
                  <l>The like, may in <hi>Confed'rate Armies</hi> see.</l>
                  <l>What hope appears, that they who can't Unite</l>
                  <l>In peaceful <hi>Councils,</hi> should agree in Fight?</l>
                  <l>With how great Ease may then our Swords divide,</l>
                  <l>That Knot, themselves already have unty'd?</l>
                  <l>My only Grief it is alass! to see</l>
                  <l>Our Foes will cost too cheap a Victory!</l>
                  <l>Mistake not then, that you for Fight prepare,</l>
                  <l>You go to Triumph, ev'n without a War.</l>
                  <l>Hast then, away, to all your Charges flie,</l>
                  <l>With Honour Conquer, or with Honour Die.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>The <hi>Grand Visiers</hi> Answer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Mighty <hi>Sultan,</hi>
                  </salute>
               </opener>
               <lg>
                  <l>Whose Will to Understand,</l>
                  <l>Is to Obey; whose Words all claim Command:</l>
                  <l>Whose Pow'rful Nod, or Sign, without the Noise</l>
                  <l>Of Words, to us sufficient are for Laws,</l>
                  <l>Which, in like Silence, each slave executes,</l>
                  <l>As if he were the humblest of your <hi>Mutes.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Such is your Pow'r; you fail not to Inspire</l>
                  <l>Your Vassals to perform, what you Require:</l>
                  <l>Your Army now no other strife does know,</l>
                  <l>But who shou'd greatest Sense of Duty show.</l>
                  <l>Your Just Resolves approving with one Voice,</l>
                  <l>They speak their glad Obedience in Applause;</l>
                  <l>Which as an hopeful Omen does presage,</l>
                  <l>They all as one Man, will your Foes engage,</l>
                  <l>While they represent to their minds in hast</l>
                  <l>The glorious Figures of Successes past.</l>
                  <l>Then paint those Scenes to <hi>Christian</hi> Eyes as plain,</l>
                  <l>As they had former Battels fought again,</l>
                  <l>Till fired with this Contemplative Review,</l>
                  <l>Our Old Conquests, exceeded be by New.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Smith.</hi> 1683.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>